字幕來源：戰地影院
翻校人員：戰地-Dingo  戰地-小心心
後期：Lee.
\an8公元前1300年
\an8過去400年  希伯來人飽受埃及人奴役
\an8為埃及造就了雕像  城市以及榮耀
\an8但是他們從未忘記過自己的故鄉
\an8以及他們的神
\an8神也從未忘記他們
法老與眾神
希泰人在卡疊什城外駐紮了16000人的部隊
It's true, the hittite army has 16,000 troops camped outside Kadesh.
他們的目的是什麼
What's less clear is why.
希泰人想要跨越邊境
The hittites are trying to cross the border.
顯而易見
Obviously.
他們還想幹嘛呢
What else would they be doing?
根據我們的情報  他們期盼我們進攻
Anticipating an invasion by us, according to our information.
他們以為我們
They think we are...
已然備戰  但我們沒有
Preparing an attack, which we are not.
我不想  也不願意坐在這
What I don't want to do, and won't do, is sit here...
乾等著希泰軍隊
And wait until we're fighting hittite armies...
兵臨城下
Outside the palace walls.
來吧
Come.
內臟都說些什麼
What do the entrails say?
內臟不會說話
They don't "say" anything.
它們只會暗示
They imply.
然後去解釋暗示
And that's open to interpretation.
那就解釋吧
So, interpret them.
我們能否先發制人贏得戰爭
We'll win or we won't in a preemptive attack?
能還是不能
It's a yes or a no.
尚不清楚
And it's not clear.
但能知道一個預言
But something else is.
戰爭中  一位首領會得救
In the battle, a leader will be saved...
救他的人某天會統治國家
And his savior will someday lead.
內臟或許應該說
Then the entrails should also say...
我們應該放棄理智
That we will abandon reason...
讓預言來引領我們
And be guided by omens.
偉大的賽克邁特
Great sekhmet...
\an8埃及獅頭女神
以你的名義  法老作飲
Pharaoh drinks in your name...
並祈禱卡疊什一戰挫敗希泰人
And prays for victory over the hittites at Kadesh.
時機一旦成熟  你就廢了她
Your first order of business when the time comes, you retire her.
我會的
I will.
真不懂我父親為什麼沒廢了她
I don't know why my father hasn't.
只是  萬一
But, just in case...
我身處險境  你就從其他路逃走
If you see me in any real danger out there, ride the other way.
我是認真的
I'm serious.
當我看著你  就像看到兩個
When I look at you, I still see the two boys...
共同成長的孩子  親如手足
Who grew up together, close as brothers.
如果有什麼原因
If, for any reason...
讓你們忘記這點
You ever forget that...
讓這個提醒你們
Let these remind you.
長度足夠在馬背上攻擊
Long enough to be effective from horseback...
卻又不會讓你拔不出來
Not so long that you trip over them.
這把是他的  我的在你那
This is his. You've got mine.
沒錯  我就是這麼安排的
That's right. That's how I want it.
你們彼此擁有
You have each other's...
保證對方安全
To keep each other safe.
答應我你們會做到
Promise me you'll do that...
直到永遠
Always.
賽提  賽提  賽提
SETI! SETI! SETI!
賽提
SETI!
在那
There!
把阿蒙隊部署在背面  瑞隊去中部
Deploy amun division to the north, ra division to the center...
卜塔隊去南面  我們帶領賽思隊做後備
And ptah to the South. And we hold Seth in reserve.
-後備  -是的
-In reserve?  -Yes.
我們應該集中兵力在中部
We should concentrate our strength in the center.
你應該集中兵力去戰鬥
You should concentrate yours on fighting.
我來指揮
Leave the generalship to me.
射箭
Fire!
衝啊
Charge!
帶走拉美西斯  走
Take ramses! Go!
走
Go!
掉頭  掉頭
Turn around! Turn around!
摩西  摩西  摩西
Moses! Moses! Moses!
摩西
Moses.
那裡發生了什麼
What happened out there?
沒什麼
Nothing.
我問了指揮官同樣的問題  他們和我撒謊
I asked the commanders the same thing. They, too, lied.
我受夠了
And I'm tired of it.
您以為有事發生
He thinks something happened.
-其實沒有  -什麼意思
-But it didn't.   -Meaning?
高階牧師  預言家
The high priestess, her prophecy.
她說她看不到誰贏
She said she couldn't see who would win.
卻看到了"首領會得救"
The other one.  "The leader will be saved..."
之類的
And so on.
你救了我兒的命
You saved my son's life?
是的
Yes.
坐下
Sit.
"謝謝"一句遠遠不夠
"Thank you" is not sufficient...
但是謝謝你
But thank you.
我知道你不相信預言之類
I know you don't believe  in omens or prophecies...
但我相信
But I do believe.
這我很敬重
And I respect that.
但這又如何
But this isn't anything.
我救了他也無任何意義
This doesn't even make any sense.
因為你不是我的血脈
Because you're not my blood.
是的
Yes.
你無法繼承我的王位
It's true, you can't succeed me.
按常理不能
Not in the usual way.
無論如何都不能
Not in any way.
光坐這想肯定不能
In any way imaginable, sitting here.
這麼說親生兒子不應該
It's horrible to say this about one's own son...
但我相信你比他更適合領導
But I trust you more than him to lead.
"希泰人的馬車
"The hittite chariotry...
"粉碎了我們的放手並開始進攻
"Crashed through our defense and began its attack.
"我發現自己被敵人包圍"
I found myself surrounded by the enemy...
"沒有衛兵  沒有盾牌
"No soldier, no shield-bearer...
"獨自面對激戰
"Facing a desperate fight for my life.
"依賴上帝的幫助
"Only with the help of the gods...
"我擊潰了我們的敵軍
"Did I defeat our attackers...
"與瑞隊會合"
"And rejoin ra division."
打住
Stop there.
有什麼你想改撰的嗎
Anything you'd like to rephrase?
沒有
No.
-我能繼續嗎  -不用了  相信剩餘情節沒問題
-Shall I go on?  -No, I'm sure the rest is fine.
下來何事
What's next?
比東
Pithom.
怎麼了
What about it?
那的形勢  以及奴隸
The situation. The slaves.
好的  拉美西斯
Fine. Ramses.
什麼
What?
去那  和總督會面  觀察情況並報告給我
Go up there, meet with the viceroy,  look around, make a report.
我
Me?
那裡終究屬於你  長點興趣吧
It will be yours someday. Take an interest in it.
還有何事
What else?
我去見總督吧
I'll go to see the viceroy.
不
No.
我去見他
I'll go.
這事不值得你去做
It's beneath you.
這事不值得任何將軍去做
It's beneath any general.
我去吧
I'll do it.
拉美西斯
Ramses...
戰場上發生的事情
Can we forget what happened...
我們忘掉它好嗎
On the battlefield?
如果換做是我
If our positions had been reversed...
我也會救你的
I would've saved your life, too.
我知道
I know. I know.
抓的很準啊
It was a good shot.
即使上帝指引著你的目標
Even if the gods did guide your aim.
血液裡有點毒液是好事
A little venom in your blood is a good thing.
可以讓你抵擋住下一次有毒的攻擊
Makes you less vulnerable to the next poisonous bite.
甚至可以抵擋我父親
Maybe even my father's.
\an8比東
歡迎來到比東
Welcome to pithom.
你得習慣這的味道
You get used to the smell.
總督似乎挺享受他在這的安逸生活
The viceroy seems to be enjoying a good share of his resources.
這裡的差事可不是誰都想幹的  我的主人
This isn't a job everyone wants to do, my lord.
為了保持他的幹勁  些許舒適安逸是有必要的
A certain degree of comfort is necessary to keep up his spirits.
你到問題所在麼  這年頭人活的太長
You know what the problem is? People live too long these days.
每年  死亡率遠低於出生率
Every year, the death rate lags further behind the birth rate.
這些人
And these people...
他們把生育當成運動一樣
They reproduce like it's a sport.
增長的勞動力是個問題
This is the problem? A growing work force?
當然不是了  生育是件好事
No, of course not. It's good for production.
當然是好事  問題是
Of course it is, but only to a point.
當眾人想要你死
When that population wants you dead...
這就會是問題
Yes, it's a problem.
所以  要麼給我更多的軍隊維持秩序
So, either I'm given more troops to maintain order...
要麼我開始縮減人口
Or I start thinning out the herd.
就因為這個荒謬的理論
You start slaughtering people...
你就想屠殺人民
For no reason other than this precarious theory...
你期望避免的事  恰恰會是你惹出來的
You will provoke the very thing you say you wish to avoid.
行啊  那就給我軍隊
Fine, then give me the troops.
我們下去和他們聊聊
Let's go down and talk to them.
為什麼呢
Why on earth?
你擔心叛亂  那我們看看你的擔心是否屬實
You're worried about sedition. Let's find out if that worry is real.
通過和他們聊聊
By talking to them?
通過和他們聊時
By looking at them...
我觀察他們
When I talk with them.
通過注視人的眼睛
You can tell a lot about somebody...
你能看出很多東西
Looking him in the eye.
我很瞭解這些
Let me tell you something...
希伯來人
About hebrews.
他們陰險  好鬥
They are a conniving, combative people.
知道在他們的語言裡
Do you know what "israelite" means...
"以色列"是什麼意思
In their own language?
"與上帝鬥爭之人"
"He who fights with God."
"與上帝角逐之人"
"He who wrestles with God."
兩者有區別
There is a difference.
或許我沒你有文化
I may not be as educated as you, which,
顯然  你想提醒我這點
apparently, you want to remind me of.
但我每天都要應付他們
But I have to deal with them every day.
我清楚自己在說什麼
I know what I'm talking about.
你不用去  我自己下去
You don't have to come. I'll go down there myself.
住手
Stop!
他為何受懲罰
Why is he being punished?
他老搗蛋  我的主人
Persistent troublemaker, my lord.
他為何在笑
Why is he smiling?
他說他沒痛覺  我的主人
He says he feels no pain, my lord.
那何必鞭打他
Then why whip him?
不是隨機召集你們來的
You were not gathered up at random.
我要求見見
I asked to see...
年長者
The elders.
快告訴我  你們祈求什麼
Come on. What do you pray for?
我們祈求再見到迦南
We pray to see canaan again.
\an8巴勒斯坦  敘利亞和黎巴嫩等地的古稱
再見到迦南
Canaan again?
你們從給見過它
You've never seen it.
我見過迦南
I've seen canaan.
比印度軍隊更殘暴的一些部落佔據著它
I've seen that it's inhabited by tribes fiercer than Egypt's military.
所以  你們回不到那了
So, you won't be returning to it...
假如你們真的打那來
Or, if you do, from it.
-上帝不這麼說  -哪位上帝
-God says otherwise. -Which God?
你們的上帝  亞伯拉罕上帝
Your God? The God of Abraham?
說你們是特殊之群的上帝
The God that says that you are special?
說你們是天選之人
That you are chosen?
過來  來
Come here. Up.
過來
Come here.
你們的上帝是錯的
He's wrong.
看得出你堅信不疑  這可是個問題
I can see you're unconvinced, and that's a problem.
因為不切實際的信仰下來是盲信
Because next to unrealistic belief lies fanaticism...
接著是叛亂  接著就是革命
And next to that, sedition, and next to that, revolution.
這一切起源於年長者
And it all starts with the elders.
你叫什麼名字
What's your name?
你叫什麼
What's yours?
我會告訴你
I'll tell you.
我叫摩西  比西亞之子
I am Moses, son of bithia...
霍倫赫布之孫
Grandson of horemheb.
記下此人和其他人的姓名
Record this one's name and the rest of them.
把下一組人帶上來
Bring in the next group.
我名叫努恩
My name is nun.
我的主人
My lord!
-站住  -放他進來
-Stop there!  -Let him through.
年長者有話要說
There's something the elder has to tell you.
這裡不方便
But not here.
告訴我何時何地
Say where and when.
今晚  禱告屋
The prayer house, tonight.
拿著
Here.
你活著回來了
I see you've survived your adventure.
抱歉又讓你等
Sorry to make you wait again.
沒在等你
I'm not waiting.
-採石場之行如何  -挺好
-How was your trip to the quarry?  -Fine.
你見到了我在應對的
You saw what I'm up against.
告訴我
Tell me...
在我離開前  還有什麼記錄需要我提供給你
Is there any more of my records I could get for you before you leave?
你能否告訴我
You can tell me...
這一切是否匯報給孟斐斯
Has all of this been reported to Memphis?
是否被批準  是否有書面記錄
Was it approved? Do you have it in writing?
當然  都記錄下來了
Of course. It's on record.
介意我們查看下嗎
So you don't mind if we check?
當然不介意
Of course I don't mind.
但不理解到底怎麼了
But I don't understand what's gone wrong.
我做了什麼讓你不開心的事
Have I done something to displease you?
如果是  如何才能讓你開心
And if so, is there any way I could please you?
別過國王般的日子
You can stop living like a king.
你不是國王
You're not one.
"你會重新佔領迦南"
"...and you will occupy the land of canaan."
迦南已被佔領
Canaan is already occupied.
上帝允諾我們能回去
God promises we will return.
作為囚徒還是死人
In chains or in coffins?
作為自由人
As free men...
去往淌著牛奶和蜂蜜的土地
Into a land flowing with milk and honey.
他們能在外等著嗎  我們並不危險
Can they at least wait outside? We're not dangerous.
去馬那等著
Wait by the horses.
你相信巧合嗎
Do you believe in coincidence?
完全相信
As much as anything else.
我認為這次不是巧合
I don't think this is one.
什麼不是巧合
What isn't?
你來比東
You coming to pithom.
你為何而來
Why did you come?
生意
Business.
坐
Sit.
你父親是誰
Who's your father?
知道你說不出他的名字
I know you don't know his name...
只知道他是法老軍隊的一名將軍
Only that he was a general in pharaoh's army...
你母親從未說起過他名字
Unnamed by your mother.
看得出這話題讓你不爽
I can see this is making you uncomfortable.
這事你會感興趣
This will interest you.
沒有什麼將軍
There was no general.
你母親
Your mother...
你喊做母親的女人  沒有孩子
The woman you call your mother, has no children.
你一出生就是奴隸
You were born a slave.
別走  別走
Don't go. Don't go.
我走是為你好
It's better for you that I do.
我走了
I'm leaving.
現在你走了  還是會回來的
If you leave now, you'll just come back...
因為你知道有些事不對勁  你一直有這感覺
Because you know something's wrong. You've always felt it.
拜託
Please.
所有人出去
Everybody out.
出去
Out.
你出生那年
The year of your birth...
有預言說會我們的領袖將誕生
There was a prophecy that our leader would be born...
來救我們於水火之中
To liberate us from our bondage.
因此  孟斐斯就下詔書
And so, there was an edict from Memphis...
命令殺害每個希伯來新生兒
To kill every firstborn Hebrew boy.
你父母不想讓這事發生
Your parents didn't wait for that to happen.
任何你活命的辦法都好過沒有辦法
Any chance of your survival was better than no chance.
他們把你交給了你姐
They handed you to your sister.
她把你放籃子裡  帶到了河邊
She took you in a basket to the banks of the river...
把你漂到了只有她知道的地方
And she floated you to where she knew...
法老帕拉美西的女兒  比西亞
Pharaoh paramesse's daughter, bithia, bathed.
比西亞收留了你和你姐  僕人米裡亞姆
Bithia took you and your sister, Miriam, as a maid...
把你們當成親生的來撫養
And raised you as her own.
她很愛你
She probably even loved you...
但從沒告訴任何人真相  包括你
But she never told you, or anyone else, the truth.
你是希伯來人
You are Hebrew.
這是真相
The truth?
真相是  這都算不上一個好故事
The truth is, it's not even that good a story.
你們這些人都擅長
And I thought you people were meant to be...
說故事
Good storytellers.
喂  奴隸
You, slave.
喂
You!
想要為這個情報領賞嗎
Do you expect a reward for this information?
能服務於你就是我們的獎賞
Our reward is being of service to you.
當然了  如果
That said, if there were...
你有比這更好的獎賞
Some token you had in mind beyond that...
我們也不會拒絕的
We wouldn't refuse it.
那這個獎賞如何
How about this, then?
我不殺你們  如何
What about if I don't kill you?
這就足夠了
That would be sufficient payment.
你們這幫人
You people.
請退下
Please leave.
請
Please.
情況如何
How did it go?
下次再談這事吧
We can talk about that another time.
現在就談
We can talk about it now...
好讓我在苦瓜臉軍醫的照料下喘息會
If only as a respite from this army of grim-faced physicians.
坐
Sit.
我自己看了下市政記錄
We're taking a thorough look at the city records...
顯然總督是個賊
And the man is clearly a thief.
真是人生莫大的諷刺啊
It's one of life's more depressing ironies...
一個渴望權力之人
That the men who crave power...
最適合當權之人  確是最不善用權力之人
Are best fitted to acquire it, and least fitted to exercise it.
怎麼了  摩西
What's wrong, Moses?
你病了
You're sick.
有事困擾著你
Something else is troubling you.
我看得出來
I can tell.
沒有  沒什麼事
No, nothing else.
願你時刻警惕
May you be alert...
得重生並受上帝庇佑
Rejuvenated and protected by the gods...
與世長存
Every moment of your eternal life.
往左
And to the left.
不  你的左邊
No, your left.
再過去點
More, more, more.
很好
Good.
它很高啊
It is tall.
紀念碑就是紀念碑
Monuments are monuments...
因為它們能做紀念
For a reason. They inspire.
這紀念碑紀念什麼
Inspire what, in this case?
紀念一切權力
In this, and in every case, power.
不管是什麼  大聲說出來吧
Say it out loud, whatever it is.
比東的總督在門外
The viceroy of pithom is outside.
議事日程是沒有他
He's not on the agenda.
讓他回比東去
He can go back to pithom until he is.
不  我們應該處理這事
No, we should deal with this.
叫他進來
Bring him in.
如果你想來請求新國王的原諒
If you came here to beg the new king's forgiveness...
想都別想
It won't work.
逮捕他
Arrest him.
請等一下
Wait, please.
能讓我說句話嗎
May I at least respond?
請求你
I beg you.
這關乎你的利益
It's in your interest.
-長話短說  -好的
-You make it short.  -I will...
只能對國王一人說
To the king alone.
我建議
My advice is that...
他和其他人離開房間
He, and the other generals, also leave the room.
是嘛
Really?
你的建議
That's your advice?
你不是他的軍師
You are not his advisor.
沒錯  你才是
That's right. You are.
沒錯
That's right.
摩西
Moses.
除了總督其他人出去
Everybody but the viceroy...
出去
Out.
有個壞消息
Terrible news.
你來了
There you are.
那麼
So...
那個總督
The viceroy.
你沒逮捕他
You didn't arrest him.
你沒有聽從我這個首席軍師的建議
You didn't take your chief advisor's advice.
沒有  他來
No, he came.
告訴我關於兩個衛兵的事
He told me of an incident involving two guards...
其中一個在襲擊中倖存了下來
One of which survived the attack.
我和他說我不在乎這種事
And I told him I did not care.
然後  他告訴了我一個難以置信的故事
And then, he told me the most unbelievable story.
他說  消息完全可靠
Told to him, he said, by very reliable sources.
我給了他點壓力
Then, when pressed...
他透露出他們都是希伯來間諜
He admitted that they were Hebrew spies.
你懂我的意思
You know what I'm talking about.
是的
Yes.
你是怎麼想的
And what do you make of it?
我覺著這很無禮  也很荒謬
I think it's offensive, and I think it's ridiculous.
是啊
Yes. Yes!
你  所有人  都是希伯來人
You, of all people, a Hebrew.
然後我說
And I said...
我要這麼相信這事
How can I believe such a story?
兄弟
Cousin...
你不能信
You can't.
如果我選擇相信這事呢  摩西
What if I take the chance of believing it, Moses?
我要怎麼做
What am I to do?
比西亞
Bithia!
母親
Mother.
那人是個賊
The man is a thief.
是我兒子發現了這事
My son discovers this.
而不是你
Not you.
他也報告給了你父親  要不是你父親他死了
And he reports it to your father, who would have hanged this thief...
就會把那人絞死
If he hadn't been dying himself.
你卻相信了他自私荒誕的謊言
You believe his feeble, self-serving lies.
我只想知道是否屬實
All I want to know is if it is true.
不要長篇大論了
I didn't ask for a tirade.
這事談的越多
To talk about this any longer...
就會越誇大
Would dignify it...
-我不想再談了  -那就回答
-And I won't do that.  -Answer the question.
是或否
Yes or no?
我在和你說話麼
Was I talking to you?
帶她上來  帶她上來
Bring her in. Bring her in.
快
Now!
米裡亞姆
Miriam!
過來  坐下
Come. Sit down.
有些事我要問你
Now, I'm going to ask you some things...
或許你覺得問題很奇怪
That are going to seem very strange to you.
只需要你如實回答
I just would like you to answer them truthfully.
你瞭解摩西嗎
How do you know Moses?
我知道我多瞭解他
You know how I know him...
還有你
And you.
我撫養了你倆
I helped raise you both.
你不是他姐  對吧
So you are not his sister, then?
當然不是
Of course not.
你也不是希伯來人
And you're not a Hebrew.
不是
No.
把你手放在桌上
Place your arm on the table.
拉美西斯
Ramses...
別做傻事
don't be stupid!
我沒在和你說話
I am not talking to you!
我在和她說
I am talking to her.
米裡亞姆  把整個手放桌上
Your whole arm on the table, Miriam.
謝謝
Thank you.
拉美西斯
Ramses...
別把事搞大了
Don't take this any further.
別把事搞大了  否則呢
Don't take this any further, or what?
別把事搞大了
Do not take this any further.
你確定要對著干
Are you quite sure about that?
把手拿開  或者馬上拿起它
Get your hand off it, or use it, now.
或許你想回答這個問題
Or perhaps you'd like to answer the question?
那我繼續了
Then I'll proceed.
米裡亞姆  我再問你一遍
Miriam, I'm going to ask you again...
如果回答仍不
And if your answer is again no...
對接下來的事我就表示遺憾了
I apologize for what happens next.
你是他姐嗎
Are you his sister?
不是
No.
是的
Yes!
不需要理由你也能殺了他  但你有理由
You don't need a reason to kill him, but you have one.
-這是叛國  -怎麼叛國了
-This was treason. -How was it treason?
他承認他知道
He just admitted he knew.
那不算是承認
That wasn't an admission!
他只是不想她的手被砍掉
Simply did not want her arm lopped off!
我從他眼裡看出來
I saw it in his eyes.
他不相信這個故事
He does not believe this story.
我也不想去相信它
I don't want to believe it!
你想要相信  因為這是除掉他的一個機會
You want to believe it, because it's an opportunity to be rid of him...
你一直都想這麼干
Which you always wanted.
我沒說要"流放"他  而是要他死
I didn't say "exiled," I said "dead."
我肯定  他會死在
That, I'm sure, will follow...
他要去的地方
Where he's going.
錫安
Khyan...
允許我和我母親說句話
Allow me to talk to my mother.
好的  長官
Yes, sir, yes.
過來  米裡亞姆
Come, Miriam.
並不是每個人都會去保護
It isn't every man who would protect a servant
對他來說微不足道的僕人
who's nothing more to him than that.
至少這個家族沒有這樣的人
Certainly no one else in this family...
包括我
Including me.
我本不該說出他想聽到的答案
I wouldn't have said what he wanted to hear.
她也是
And neither would she.
我們非常愛你
That's how much we love you.
"我們"
"We"?
這不是真的
It's not true.
是真的
It is true.
我把你帶到河邊時  你戴著這個
You were wearing this when I brought you to the river.
我把它摘下來  目的很明確
I took it off you for obvious reasons.
那才是你
That's you.
這是你和你母親之間維繫的物
The connection between you and our mother.
你姐救了你
Your sister saved your life.
現在你救了她
Now you saved hers...
摩西
Moshe.
米裡亞姆
Miriam.
抱歉  長官
Sorry, sir.
摩西
Moses!
我沒啥可偷的了
I have nothing to steal.
我的馬死了
My horse is dead.
我們不是來要你的馬  摩西
We're not here for your horse, moshe.
\an8紅海  蒂朗海峽
再高一點
A little bit higher.
你要幹嘛
What are you doing?
別停  繼續幹活
Don't stop. Keep working.
喂  給我們的羊弄點水
You, get water for our goats.
喂
You.
還沒輪到你
Wait your turn.
把你們的羊從水槽那趕走
Move your animals away from the troughs.
又屬於你們的了
It's yours again.
你從哪來
Where are you from?
西面
West of here.
你要去哪
Where are you going?
東面
East.
你犯了何事
What did you do?
什麼意思
What do you mean?
你犯了什麼罪
You committed some crime?
恕我直言
With respect...
您女兒邀請我來用餐
Your daughters invited me for some food.
沒說會審問我
They did not tell me there would be an interrogation.
抱歉
I'm sorry.
我只是好奇
I'm just curious.
歡迎你在飯前清洗下身子
You are welcome to get cleaned up before dinner...
如果你願意的話
If that appeals to you...
今晚你也可以留下
And stay the night if you want...
明天繼續趕路
Before continuing on...
不管你要去哪
To wherever it is.
謝謝你
Thank you.
和我描述下孟斐斯吧
Describe Memphis to someone...
我從未有機會也不會有機會去那
Who's never been there and never will.
它
It's...
我不想用"文明"這詞
I don't want to say "civilized"...
不想冒犯你們  但它確實是文明城市
Because I don't want to offend, but it is civilized.
那裡不僅僅是羊多
There's more there than sheep and goats.
這裡也不僅僅是羊多
There's more here than that.
真的  有什麼
Really? Where?
抱歉  我真無禮
I'm sorry, that was rude.
我真無禮
That was rude.
雖然住在這  但我並不無知
I'm not ignorant just because I live here.
看得出來
I can see that.
我敢說
I can tell you one thing.
目前為止
This is by far...
在我來的和要去的地方
The nicest place...
這裡地方最棒
Between here and there.
你要走了
And so you're leaving?
當然
Of course.
我這樣的人不屬於這裡
There's nothing here for someone like me.
什麼時候
When?
今天
Today?
牢記此時此刻
Remember this moment in time...
誓言之後
For after these vows...
你將向世界宣佈
You shall say to the world...
"這是我丈夫"這是我妻子"
"This is my husband." "This is my wife."
我  西坡拉
I, zipporah...
我  摩西
I, Moses...
-西坡拉  我願意  -摩西  我願意
-Accept you, zipporah...  -Accept you, Moses...
接受你真正的樣子
To be no other than yourself.
深愛我所瞭解的你
Loving what I know of you...
信賴我所不知道的你
Trusting what I do not yet know.
相敬如賓
With respect...
真心誠意
For your integrity...
忠貞不渝
And faith...
相親相愛
In your abiding love for me.
不管生活如何
In all that life may bring us...
我都承諾愛你
I pledge my love.
誰讓你幸福
Who makes you happy?
你啊
You do.
你生命中什麼最重要
What's the most important thing in your life?
你啊
You are.
你想去哪裡
Where would you rather be?
哪也不去
Nowhere.
何時離我而去
And when will you leave me?
永遠不會
Never.
繼續
Proceed.
\an89年後
我說婆賽
I said "per se."
我不想討論我墓穴
I don't want to discuss my tomb, per se.
我只想知道你為什麼一直喜歡討論我的墓穴
I want to discuss why you seem to want to discuss it all the time.
恕我直言
Respectfully...
這是你繼位以來第一個建築項目
It should have been your first construction order on taking the throne.
你可以想像  工程之大
It'll be a big project, as you might imagine.
顯然  我的宮殿也是
So is my house, apparently.
宮殿有什麼問題
Is there a problem with the palace?
它還沒完工
It's not done.
不會太久的
It won't be long now.
幾個月前你也這麼說  而我住的像個
You said that months ago. Meanwhile I'm living there like...
貝都因人
A bedouin.
趕緊完工
Get it done.
快點
Faster!
是否需要我殺掉點人
Or do I have to kill somebody?
我們都瞭解你的意思了
I think you made your point.
扔的好準  父親
Good throw, father.
只要瞄高一點
Just aim a little higher.
差點
Almost.
你去過山頂嗎
Have you ever been to the top?
沒有
No.
想去嗎
Would you like to?
母親說禁止去那
Mother says it's forbidden.
誰禁止
By who?
我們的上帝
Our God.
Our God...
不允許我們爬山
Stops us from climbing mountains?
不是每座山
Not every Mountain.
只那一座
Just that one.
它是上帝之山
It's God's Mountain.
你讓他感到困惑
You're confusing him.
不是我本意
I'm not trying to.
讓我們的孩子沒有信仰的成長  這好嗎
Is it good for our boy to grow up believing in nothing?
信仰自己的成長  不好嗎
Is it bad to grow up believing in yourself?
-這是我的信仰  -我知道
-It's my faith.  -I know.
-這也是他的  -我理解
-And it's his, too.  -I understand.
當他大了再做選擇
He can make up his mind when he's older.
-對  -就和你一樣
-Yes.  -Just like you.
很多方面他已經很像我
He's a lot like me already.
摩西
Moshe.
救救我
Help me!
我的腿可能斷了
I think my leg is broken.
不單如此
More than that.
你說什麼
What did you say?
你是誰
Who are you?
我是個牧羊人
I'm a Shepherd.
我以為你是個將軍
I thought you were a general.
我需要位將軍
I need a general.
為什麼
Why?
去打仗
To fight.
還能幹嘛
Why else?
對抗誰
Fight who?
為何而戰
For what?
我想你知道
I think you know.
你該去看看你的人民現在的處境
I think you should go and see what's happening to your people now.
否則他們終不得安寧
He won't be at peace until you do.
或在你看來
Or are they not people...
他們不是你的人民
In your opinion?
你是誰
Who are you?
我就是我
I am.
你撞到頭了
You were hit on the head.
之後你所看到的
Anything you saw...
或你以為你看到的
Or think you saw afterwards...
都是幻覺
Was an effect of that.
風暴
The storm...
在我撞到頭之前風暴就開始了
The storm started before I was hit on the head.
-那不是風暴  -好了  好了
-It was not a storm. -Fine, fine.
風暴是真的
The storm was something.
風暴不是真的
It was something else.
-但你腦子裡全是那個孩子  -你怎麼知道
-But the boy was all in your head. -How do you know?
你怎麼知道
How do you know?
因為上帝不是個孩子
Because God isn't a boy!
那他看起來像什麼
Then what does he look like?
描述下  給我描述下
Describe him. Describe him to someone like me.
你說話聽起來像什麼知道嗎
Do you know what you sound like?
聽起來我像在妄想
Yes. I sound delusional.
是的
Yes.
-你需要好好休息  -是的  是的
-You just need more rest. -Yes, yes.
我有事要告訴你
I have to tell you something.
我對你沒完全坦誠
I've not been completely honest with you.
是什麼
About what?
我的身份
About who I am.
我所做所為以及我的身份
About what I've done and who I was.
還有我的感受
And how I feel.
-關於你對我的感受  -不是
-About what you feel about me?  -No.
對於你的感受我一直是真誠的
No, I've been honest about that.
休息吧
Rest.
-休息  -別離開我
-Rest.  -Don't leave me.
不  不
No. No.
摩西
Moshe.
革舜
Gershom?
你在這幹嘛
What are you doing out here?
沒什麼
Nothing.
睡不著
I can't sleep.
在擔心我
Are you worried about me?
是的
Yes.
別擔心
Don't.
我沒事
I'll be fine.
那是什麼
What's that?
它看起來像什麼
What's it look like?
進來
Come inside.
Come inside!
你拿它們要做什麼
What are you going to do with all that?
確保我能再見到你
Make sure I see you again.
放下它  你一直能見著我
Put it down and you can see me forever.
這是什麼意思
What's this mean?
這是某個我認識的人名
It's someone I used to know.
我不會一去不回
This is not forever.
還會回來見你
I will see you again.
相信我嗎
Do you believe me?
乖乖的
Good for you.
不要說一些人們想要聽的話
Don't ever just say what people want to hear.
我會
But I will...
我會再見到你
I will see you again.
能替我保管好這個嗎
Will you keep this for me?
革舜
Gershom.
革舜  看著我
Gershom, please look at me.
什麼樣的上帝會讓一個男人
What kind of God tells a man...
離開他的家庭
To leave his family?
如果你能理解  我也會理解
If you understand it, I'll understand it.
我不理解
I don't.
所以回答不了你
So I can't answer that question.
如果這是信仰的意思  我願意背棄自己信仰
If that's what faith means, I will trade mine...
維護你的信仰
To keep you.
別碰我
Don't touch me.
走
Go.
Go!
老爹  能給點牛奶嗎
Father, have you some milk to spare?
好的
Yes.
你來自哪裡
Where did you come from?
我來自海邊
I come from the sea.
這條路狹窄兇險
It's a narrow and dangerous path.
謝謝你  老爹
Thank you, father.
耶和華  我記得你
Joshua. I remember you.
你仍沒有痛覺
Do you still feel no pain?
看著馬
Keep your eye on the horse.
-謝謝  -歡迎回來  兄弟
-Thank you. -Welcome back, brother.
亞倫
Aaron...
你哥哥
Your brother.
以他瑪
Ithamar.
以他瑪  他
Ithamar, this...
是你著名的摩西叔叔
Is your famous Uncle Moses.
曾是埃及王子
He was once a prince of Egypt.
我沒事
I'm fine.
大家都沒事
Everybody's fine.
睡的真香啊  我的孩子
You sleep so well, my boy...
因為你知道我們都愛著你
Because you know you are loved.
我就沒法睡好
I've never slept so well.
我應該稱呼你為
I'm told I should address you...
偉大的拉美西斯
As ramses the great, now.
摩西
Moses...
你還活著
You're alive.
-很高興你還活著  -真的
-I'm glad you're alive.  -Really?
所以你才派了兩名殺手來殺我
Is that why you only sent two assassins to kill me?
是我母親
My mother.
-別怪她  -是她想你死
-Don't blame her. -Yes, she wanted you dead.
你覺得會是誰把劍藏在你能找到的地方
Who do you think hid your sword where you would find it?
摩西
Moses.
我不是來
I'm not here...
奪取你的王位
To take your throne.
也不是關於你很擔心的那個預言
It's not about the prophecy that worries you so much.
而是其他事情
This is something else.
有人告訴我
I have been told...
這裡的情況變得
That things here have become...
更糟了
Much worse.
這裡的情況從未如此好過  摩西
Things are better than they ever have been, Moses.
不
No.
-我們有秩序  -秩序
-We have order.  -Order?
奴隸們
The slaves...
他們的屍體日夜在燃燒
Their bodies burn night and day now.
我親眼所見
I've seen it with my own eyes.
你稱那是秩序
You call that order?
他們是奴隸
They're slaves.
-不  他們不是  -你覺得是什麼
-No, they're not. -What would you expect?
他們是埃及人  像埃及人那樣對待他們
They're Egyptians, they should be treated as Egyptians.
他們應享有同樣的權利
They should have the same rights...
他們的勞動應該有報酬
They should be paid for their work...
否則你就得放他們走
Or you must set them free.
他們不是埃及人
They are not Egyptians.
摩西  他們是奴隸  你覺得呢
They are slaves, Moses. What else do you expect?
如果像動物那樣
They wouldn't know what to do...
讓他們自食其力  他們就不知道該怎麼辦了
If all of a sudden they were left to fend for themselves like animals.
別稱他們為動物
Do not call them animals!
從經濟角度來看
Listen,from an economic standpoint alone...
你的要求
What you're asking...
絕對會產生問題
Is problematic to say the least.
我沒指望你直截了說"是"
I didn't expect to hear a simple yes.
但我也不想聽你直接說"不"
But I do not want to hear a simple no.
你是在和我說"不"嗎
Is that what you are telling me? Are you saying no?
我沒有說"不"
I'm not saying no.
我需要時間
I'm saying time.
時間
Time.
你在聽從希伯來人
You're listening to hebrews.
我沒聽從希伯來人
I'm not listening to hebrews.
那你在和誰交談
Who are you talking to?
上帝
God.
哪位上帝
Which God?
你不用認真考慮他的提議
You're not seriously considering his proposal.
那是提議嗎
Is it a proposal?
如果一個人拿著劍指著你的喉嚨
If a man is holding a dagger to your throat, minister?
-它是提議嗎  -我說錯了
-Is it? -I stand corrected.
那是要求
That's a demand.
他失去理智了
He has lost his mind.
他找到了一位上帝  他的上帝
He's found a God. His God.
而不是我們的上帝
Not one of ours...
所以我想要摩西
So I would like Moses...
我想要摩西死
I want Moses dead.
聽懂了嗎
Did you hear me?
是的
Yes.
退下吧
Then, go.
還有
And...
他的家人
His family, too.
摩西
Moses.
摩西在哪
Where's Moses?
摩西  摩西在哪
Moses? Where's Moses?
摩西
Moses...
他的家人
His family.
他們在哪
Where are they?
他不是摩西
This is not Moses.
這不是他家人
This is not his family.
他這個男人
This is a man...
他的妻子
His wife...
以及他的孩子
And his child...
他們在被問及"他在哪"這個簡單問題時
Who when asked the simple question, "where is he?"...
回答了"我們不知道"
Answered, "we don't know."
今晚  帶著這一幕回家
Carry this image home with you tonight...
商討下你們為什麼要保護他
And discuss why you would protect him...
記住明天此時
Knowing that tomorrow at this time...
又會有一個家庭
There will be another family...
和他們一樣
Where this one is.
後天
And another the day after.
再後天
And the day after that.
會不會輪到你家
Dare I say yours?
去吧
Go ahead.
我想參加戰鬥
I want to join the fight.
進去
In there.
耶和華  你用的膝蓋
Joshua, use your knee.
很好
It's good.
雙眼睜開
Both eyes open!
搭箭  開弓
Nock! Draw!
射箭
Loose!
前進
Advance.
搭箭  開弓
Nock. Draw.
射箭
Loose!
開弓
Draw!
射箭
Loose!
開弓
Draw!
射箭
Loose!
再來
Again!
戰爭分兩種
There are two kinds of warfare.
每一種跟人數有關
Each is dictated by numbers.
人數多
With greater numbers...
你迎頭而上進攻
You attack the enemy head on!
直擊要害
You stab it in the heart!
人數少  就從側面進攻
With fewer numbers, you come at it from the side.
取其七寸
You cut off the blood...
斷其筋脈
That pumps the heart.
切斷軍火供給
The army supply lines.
不
No!
切斷人民的供給
The people's supply lines.
他們的食物
Their food...
他們的財物
Their property...
他們的安逸
Their comfort.
那會得到什麼
What would that achieve?
一切
Everything.
只有埃及人民
Only the Egyptian people...
才能逼迫他接受我們
Can force him to accept our demands...
自由的要求  我們必須迫使他們
For freedom. We must force them...
逼迫他同意
To make him say yes!
是不是
Yes?
是
Yes!
是不是
Yes?
是
Yes!
跟著我
With me!
準備
Ready.
你不打算想想辦法了
You're not going to do anything?
我可沒這麼說
I didn't say that.
你去哪了
Where have you been?
看你如何失敗
Watching you fail.
消耗戰需要時間
Wars of attrition take time.
按這速度  你要花上幾年
At this rate, you'll take years...
一輩子
A generation.
我準備好打這麼久的仗了
I am prepared to fight for that long.
我沒有
I'm not.
我想我們有點起色了
I thought we were making progress.
你卻不耐煩了
Now, you're impatient.
400年的奴役都過去了
After 400 years of slavery.
直到現在  我是唯一無所事事的人嗎
Am I the only one sitting here who's done nothing about this until now?
我知道
I do know...
一些軍事戰術
A few things about military action.
如果你不願聽從我
Still, if you're not going to listen to me...
為何你要讓我遠離
Then why did you take me away...
我的家庭
From my family?
不是我
I didn't.
是你
You did.
你不需要我
ou don't need me.
或許不需要
Maybe not.
那我該怎麼辦  啥都不干
So what do I do? Nothing?
現在起
For now...
你就看著
You can watch.
\an8上帝要降下"十災"
神聖的凱貝潔特女神  我謙卑的召喚你
Divine goddess kebechet, I humbly call upon you...
來淨化我們賴以生存的水域
To purify the waters of our life-giving river.
還要多久
How long will it take?
不會太久
Not long.
還要稍微久點
But longer than that.
拉美西斯  拉美西斯
Ramses! Ramses!
什麼事
Yes?
夠了
Enough!
想想辦法
Do something!
他們只是青蛙
They're just frogs.
退後  退後
Back away, back away.
不乾淨
Unclean.
不  不  不  別喝
No, no, no. Don't drink.
不乾淨
Unclean.
我都知道  尼羅河攜帶一定數量的泥土
The nile, as we know, carries a certain amount of Clay.
今年泥土數量異常得多
This year there's much more of it than usual...
漂浮在河流中  沉積在河床上
Drifting in on the currents, settling on the riverbeds...
並被鱷魚給攪渾了
And kicked up by the wild thrashing of the crocodiles.
這種渾濁
This thrashing not only...
不但大大改變了水的顏色  也污染了水
Dramatically changed the color of the water, but it fouled it...
以至於把魚殺死了
To the point of killing the fish.
但青蛙  我們都知道
But frogs, as we know...
在不得已的情況下  他們會跳出水面
Can get out of the water, when they have to.
現在就這情況
Which they did.
但青蛙仍然需要水
But frogs still need water...
但是在我們城市的路上找不到水
And when they can't find it in the streets of our city...
它們就怎麼樣
They what?
它們死了
They die?
They die!
然後腐爛
And then they decompose.
然後虱子  蛆和蒼蠅都來了
And then the gnats come and the maggots come and the flies come.
然後
And then...
然後什麼
And then what?
蒼蠅會死
The flies die.
快說
Speak up.
在希伯來人那找到的
It's in Hebrew.
希伯來人
Hebrew?
念出來
Read it.
"這些災難
"These catastrophes...
"乃上帝所賜
"Are the work of God...
"災難還沒結束  只會變得更糟
"And they have not finished. They will get worse.
"看在彼此份上
"We need to reach a settlement...
"我們需要達成協議"
"For both our sakes."
上帝所賜
So, the work of God.
我給你們的協議
Here is my settlement to you.
就是工作量翻倍
Work quotas shall be doubled...
不會給你們稻草
And you will get no straw...
來搬運磚塊
To make your bricks.
或許你們的上帝
Perhaps your God...
會提供給你
Will provide it for you.
起初我很感動
I was impressed at first.
現在不是了
Not anymore.
這殃及了所有人
This is affecting everyone.
你在懲罰誰
So, who are you punishing?
他怎麼了
What's wrong with him?
生病了
It's sick.
這是什麼
What is this?
-你幹的  -不是我
-Did you do this?  -Not me.
-你幹的  -不  不
-Is this you?  -No, no!
它怎麼了
What's happened to him?
我們的醫療已有長足進步
We have made great strides in medicine.
然而
However,
仍然有一些疾病我們所不瞭解
there are still a few hidden diseases that we don't completely understand.
動物也不例外
Animals are not exempt...
我猜想
And there is some conjecture...
這些瘟病可能來自最小的生物
That these maladies can migrate from the smallest creature.
比如
Like a...
蒼蠅
A fly.
你最近去過河邊嗎
Have you been out to the river lately?
我再次祈求凱貝潔特女神
I appealed to kebechet again...
以及其他六位神靈
And six more gods.
就這些
Is that it?
收手了沒
Are you done?
我收手了
I am.
你不出現  是想說明什麼
Are you trying to say something with your absence?
想羞辱我嗎
Is it meant to humble me?
沒用的
Because it will not!
初步估計
Initial reports suggest...
超過一千萬平方公尺的莊稼被毀
More than 10 million square cubits of crops have been lost.
軍需官建議我們返一部分糧食
The quartermaster has suggested we return a portion...
來補給民用倉庫
Of the supplement to the civil granary.
仁善之舉
An act of mercy.
你的人民在挨餓
Your people are starving.
你想我也挨餓是嗎
Are you suggesting that I should starve, too?
不
No.
人民有足夠的水
People have plenty of water.
他們能忍受住
They will endure.
瞄準
Aim!
射箭
Fire!
瞄準
Aim!
射箭
Fire!
是你嗎
Is that you?
摩西
Moses?
兄弟
Brother?
你是來談判的
Have you come to negotiate?
我準備好了
Because I'm ready...
我給你個條件
As I have an offer for you.
這類事情再發生一次
One more thing happens...
我也會降我的瘟疫
And I will bring my own plague to you.
每個還不會走路的
You see, every Hebrew child...
希伯來孩童
Not yet walking...
將永遠沒機會走路
They never shall.
因為我會把他們淹死在尼羅河
Because I will drown them in the nile.
就像你本該的那樣
As you should have been.
你敢說這些不是你造成的
You say that you didn't cause all this?
你的上帝干的
Your God did?
我就是上帝  我就是上帝
I am the God! I am the God!
讓我們瞧瞧誰殺人更有效率
So, let's just see who's more effective at killing.
你
You.
你的上帝
This God.
還是我
Or me.
你能來真好
Nice of you to come.
他達到你的要求了嗎
He's given you what you asked?
還沒有  但他的人民在反對他
Not yet. But his own people are turning against him.
-他的軍隊呢  -也會的
-And his army?  -It will.
我不同意
I disagree.
還要發生更大的災難
Something worse has to happen.
我不同意
I disagree.
-任何災難將會  -將會怎樣
-Anything more would be...  -Would be what?
你想說什麼
What were you about to say?
殘忍  不人道
Cruel? Inhumane?
這些人和我一起長大
It's not easy to see...
看著他們受難很不好受
The people who I grew up with suffering this much.
那些沒和你一起成長的人們呢
What about the people you didn't grow up with?
你對他們的感受是什麼
What thought did you give to them?
你始終覺得他們不是你的人們  對吧
You still don't think of them as yours, do you?
只要拉美西斯還有軍隊支撐著
As long as ramses has an army behind him...
形勢就不會改觀
Nothing will change.
任何災難都是復仇
Anything more is just revenge!
復仇  經過400年的殘酷鎮壓
Revenge? After 400 years of brutal subjugation?
這些法老幻想著他們是活神仙
These pharaohs who imagine they're living gods,
他們不過是肉體凡胎
they're nothing more than flesh and blood.
我要他們跪下來求我住手
I want to see them on their knees, begging for it to stop!
我受夠了和一個信使交談
I'm tired of talking with a messenger!
將軍
General!
我聽到了拉美西斯最終的威脅
I have heard ramses' final threat.
讓我告訴你下來會發生什麼
So, let me tell you what's going to happen next.
不  不
No. No.
你不能那麼做
You cannot do this.
我不想再參合這事
I want no part of this!
停住
Stay!
-站住  -摩西
-Hold!  -Moses?
讓他過來
Leave him.
-希安  -摩西
-Khyan. -Moses.
我本可以殺了你
I could have you killed.
我不這麼覺得
I don't think so.
除非你親自動手
Unless you do it yourself.
你的士兵放我進來的
Your own soldiers let me in.
我不想再談判了
I am not negotiating anymore.
我來的目的不是談判
That's not why I'm here.
我是來告訴你  有事要發生
I came to tell you that something is coming...
它已經超出我的掌控
That is out of my control.
它會殃及成千上萬人
Something that will affect thousands...
成千上萬居民
And thousands of citizens.
它會影響到你個人
And it will affect you very personally
除非接受我的要求
unless you accept what I've asked for...
並在太陽落山前
And announce it publicly...
公之於眾
Before the sun goes down.
拉美西斯
Ramses...
別背對我
Do not turn your back on me!
這不是私人恩怨
This has nothing to do with you and I.
遠遠不是
This is far beyond that.
這關乎埃及人存亡  懂嗎
This is about Egypt's survival. Do you understand?
日落前
Sunset.
否則  就太遲了
After that, it will be too late.
什麼太遲了
What will be too late?
保護好你的孩子
You protect your child.
今晚保護好你的孩子
You protect your child tonight.
我的孩子
My child?
這是威脅嗎
Is that a threat?
這是威脅嗎  摩西
Is that a threat? Moses!
摩西
Moses!
告訴大家
Tell everyone...
去宰一頭羊
To slaughter a lamb...
今晚用羊血
And mark their doors...
在門以及門框上
And their doorposts tonight...
做標記
With its blood.
為什麼
Why?
如果我錯了  就可惜了羊兒
Pity the lambs if I am wrong.
如果我是對的
If I'm right...
我們得祈禱它們得到永生
We will bless them for eternity.
本奴  本奴
Bennu? Bennu?
不
No!
拉美西斯
Ramses?
Ramses.
拉美西斯
不
No!
撒迦利亞
Zechariah?
跪下
Kneel!
出去
Get out!
兇手
Murderer!
孩童殺手
Child killer!
他們的孩子昨晚死了
Their children died last night.
我的孩子也是
As did mine.
是你的上帝干的
Is this your God?
孩童殺手
A killer of children?
什麼樣的上帝會有如此"傑作"
What kind of fanatics worship such a God?
昨晚希伯來孩童沒一個死的
No Hebrew child died last night.
滾
Get...
滾出去
Out.
走
Go.
你們每個人
Every one of you!
滾
Go!
回到你們夢想的迦南去吧
Go to canaan if that's what you want.
回到你們夢中的故土
Back to the homeland of your dreams.
滾吧
But go!
聽從你的命令
As you command.
這是我走過的路
This is the route I took.
從這裡  我們往南去紅海
From here, we go South to the red sea.
海峽在這  有點潮水  但能步行穿過
The straits are here. At low tide, we can cross on foot.
知道為什麼你能睡這麼香嗎  我的孩子
You know why you sleep so well, my boy?
因為你知道我們都愛你
Because you know you are loved.
恕我直言
With respect...
如果我們不抓個40萬奴隸回來
If we're going to recapture 400,000 slaves...
我們就需要超過3個師的人
We might need more than three divisions.
我們不抓任何奴隸
We're not recapturing anyone.
前進
Forward!
我們應該休息
We should rest.
不
No.
到了紅海才安全
We're not safe until we cross the sea.
摩西
Moshe!
拉美西斯
Ramses...
帶著4000人
4,000 men...
一千輛馬車
A thousand chariots.
離我們多遠
How far behind us?
4天路程
Four days.
要是他們馬不停蹄  不到4天
Less, if they don't rest the horses.
拉美西斯
Ramses!
馬需要歇息
We need to rest the horses...
士兵們也是
And the men!
海峽在那條路
The straits are that way.
最長  最好走的路
The longest, easiest route...
在西海岸
Is down the Western coast.
或者我們穿過山脈
Or we go through the mountains.
穿過山脈
The mountains?
為什麼  為什麼不走那條路
Why? Why don't we take that route?
我們可以  拉美西斯也可以
We can, but so can ramses.
山路險峻
The Mountain passes are dangerous...
但對於拉美西斯的馬車來說太窄
But they are too narrow for ramses' chariots.
他追不上  能給我們爭取點時間
He couldn't follow. That would give us needed time.
上帝和你怎麼說
What does God tell you?
走山路
The mountains.
能成功嗎
Can we make it?
前進
Forward!
走哪條路
Which way from here?
待在這
Stay here.
我們需要你的幫助
We need your help.
我不知道身在何方
I don't know where I am.
你不幫我
You won't help me?
You won't help them.
這條路
This way!
出發
Move out!
這條路
This way!
你確定
Are you sure?
非常確定
I'm very sure.
憑我們的裝備  你確定我們能翻過山
I mean, are you sure we can make it across with our equipment...
我們的馬車呢
Our chariots?
他們都不覺得他們的裝備能翻過去
They didn't think they could with theirs.
他們如何知道
How would they know?
他們又沒走過那裡
They've never been here.
摩西或許知道
Moses may have.
漲潮還是退潮
Is this high tide or low tide?
沒關係
Doesn't matter.
這不是海峽  對吧
This isn't the straits, is it?
不是
No.
你知道我們在哪嗎
Do you even know where we are?
是的
Yes!
我們正在某個地方  前有大海
We're at a point on the earth where there is a sea ahead...
後有追兵
And an army behind!
現在怎麼辦
So now what?
不管有沒追兵
Army or no army...
我們都要休息
We have to rest.
我誤導了所有人
I have misled all of them.
我拋家棄子
I have abandoned my family.
卻辜負了你
I have failed you.
我並不是自認為的那樣
I'm not what I thought I was.
那是什麼
What is it?
洋流
The current.
水流很急
It's strong.
我們要涉過去
We need to cross here.
現在就涉過去
We need to cross now!
我們從這過去
We cross here.
We cross here!
大家準備
Ready yourselves!
我們從這過去
We cross here!
快去告訴他們  去
Go tell them! Go!
你的命令
Your orders...
就像是埃及人的皮鞭
Are like the lash of the Egyptian whip.
我們不再是奴隸
We are no longer slaves.
你們尚未自由
And yet, you are not free.
你看不到
You have lost sight...
你們先祖之地
Of canaan...
迦南
Land of your forebears.
你們賜予我信任
You have honored me...
我深感榮幸
With your trust.
現在我賜予你們我的信仰
Now I honor you with my faith.
跟隨我  你們終將自由
Follow me and you will be free!
留下則會滅亡
Stay and you will perish.
不用害怕
Do not be afraid!
上帝與我們同在
God is with us!
走  大家準備
Go! Ready yourselves!
走
Go!
上帝與我們同在
God is with us!
傳話出去  我們從這過去
Pass the word! We cross here!
盡快收拾好你們的東西
As quickly as you can, gather your things...
站成一隊
And form in groups!
快
Quickly!
快點
Come on!
穩住
Steady!
靠右  靠右  貼緊
To the right, to the right! Tight!
繼續前進
Keep moving!
沒什麼好害怕的
There's nothing to fear!
別擔心  你們很安全
Don't worry! You'll be safe!
靠右  靠右
Keep to the right! Keep to the right!
拉美西斯
Ramses!
停
Stop!
停  停
Stop! Stop!
走
Go.
繼續前進
Keep moving!
繼續前進  前進
Keep moving! Forward!
那裡
There.
耶和華
Joshua!
亞倫
Aaron!
跑
Run!
大家跑啊
Everyone, run!
跑
Move!
跑到海邊
Run to shore!
摩西
Moshe.
我們必須離開
We must leave!
拉美西斯
Ramses!
沖
Go!
拉美西斯  停
Ramses, stop!
所有人  掉頭
All! Turn around!
掉頭
Turn around!
錫安
Khyan!
離開
Leave.
弟弟
Brother...
馬上離開  這是命令
Leave now! That's an order!
來呀  你回不了頭了
Come! You'll never make it back!
沖
Go!
快
Faster!
這只有我
It's just me here.
坐
Sit.
我的家裡
My family...
離這不遠
Is not far from here.
你的家人
Your family?
我另外個家  我妻子和孩子
My other family. My wife, my son.
我在想
I was thinking...
或許我能說服他們
Maybe I could convince them...
說服他們加入我們  但或許
Convince them to join us, but perhaps that's...
那不是明智之舉
Perhaps that's not wise.
他們當然應該過來
Of course they should come.
我們還有很長的路要走
We have a long way to go.
路長夢多
A lot can happen.
如果
And then...
如果我們到了那
We get there, if we get there.
你覺得他們會讓我們定居在迦南嗎
You don't think they'll let us settle in canaan?
他們會視我們為入侵者
They'll see us as invaders.
他們別無選擇  我們比任何部落的人都多
They won't have a choice. We're as big as any tribe.
我們的人數可以匹敵一個國家  反倒讓我更擔心
We're as big as a nation of tribes and that concerns me even more.
為什麼
Why?
這麼多人
This many people?
你還用問
You have to ask?
但我們目標一致
But we all have the same goal.
現在是
We do now.
但不再逃亡以後呢
What happens when we stop running?
偉大的
Ramses...
拉美西斯
The great.
謝謝
Thank you.
革舜
Gershom.
你按你說的做了嗎
Did you do what you said?
我說什麼了
What did I say?
你願意犧牲你的信仰
That you would trade your faith...
來維護我的信仰
To keep me.
沒有
No.
很好
Good.
現在你更需要堅信你的信仰
You may need it more than ever now.
他們是誰
Who are they?
他們是我的人民
They're my people.
是誰讓你幸福
Who makes you happy?
你啊
You do.
你生命中什麼最重要
What is the most important thing in your life?
你啊
You are.
你何時離我而去
When will I leave you?
永遠不會
Never.
我能繼續嗎
May I proceed?
繼續吧
Proceed.
你覺得這個怎麼樣
What do you think of this?
要是不同意
I wouldn't do it...
我也不會這麼做
If I didn't agree.
沒錯
That's true.
我注意到你
I've noticed that about you.
並不總能同意我
You don't always agree with me.
我注意到  你也是
Nor you me, I've noticed.
但我們仍在這  說著話
Yet here we are, still speaking.
可惜說不了太久
But not for much longer.
領袖會更迭
A leader can falter...
但石頭
But stone...
永不腐朽
Will endure.
這些法律會代替你引領他們
These laws will guide them in your stead.
如果你不同意
If you disagree...
就該把錘子放下
You should put down the hammer.